Princeton University Library Collection of Modern Greek Materials, 1677-1967: Finding Aid C0958
Manuscripts Division
- Skaltsounes, I., 1879-1880; 1 box
  - Skaltsounes, I., 1879; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 10)
    2 letters regarding the criminal and political law of Crete, 1879.
- Societe des Sciences d'Athenes, 1894-1908; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 11)
  AM 2005-96
  Printed brochure of organization (1894), membership letter (1908) for Roland Bonaparte, and cover letter (n.d., in French) accompanying the 2 items.
- Soutsos, Michael Vodas, 1828-1839; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 12)
  9 letters.
- "Ston Hellēnoitalikon Polemon tou 1940", 1 box (Box 4, Folder 13)
  AMs diary compiled by the leader of the "skapanisses" of the National Youth Organization (E.O.N.)
- Stratford de Redcliffe, Stratford Canning, Viscount, 1786-1880, 1826 May 25; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 14)
  AM 2002-127
  LS (1826) to "Captain Admilton," written from Cosntantinople, regarding the future of Greece and Turkey.
- Su l'etat Financier de la Grece, 1835; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 15)
  AMs (ca. 1835-1836) on the financial state of Greece in 1835.
- Tableau d'importation et d'exportation de commune general de l'ile de Crete, 1834; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 16)
  AM 2010-54
  D, table.
- Tachtsēs, Kōstas, 1954-1988; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 17)
  AM 1997-107, AM 2002-110
  Correspondence with Ben Sonnenberg and other materials.
- Theotokes, Emmanouel Baron, 1821 September 17; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 18)
  AM 1997-108
  ALS to Charles Peroy in London, 17 September 1821.
- Vogue, E. M. de, 1887; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 19)
  AM 2005-95
  "Lettres Atheniennes, par Mr. le Cte. Charles de Mouy, Librarie Plon, 1887," AMsS, 9 pp.
- Wheler, George, Sir, 1650-1723, 1677 March 22; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 20)
  AM 2005-40
  ALS (1677, in French) to Jacob Spon.
- Young, Frank A. H, 1860-1861; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 21)
  2 ALsS (1860, 1861) to "Mrs. Dunham" describing his missionary life in Turkey (Constantinople, Trebizond).
- Zosimus II, 1736-1737; 1 box (Box 4, Folder 22)
  AM 1997-104
  3 letters (1736-1737) to Georg Tonneman, S.J.; 1 document, 1736.
- Hē en Athēnais Hetaireia tēs Physikēs Historias, 1836; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2009-131)
  Consists of an autograph manuscript letter (34 x 21.3 cm) of the Society of Natural History at Athens signed by Dēm. Alex. Maurokordatos, secretary of the Society, to a General of the English National Guard regarding their acceptance as a member of the Society. It is acoompanied by the diploma of membership, partly printed/partly handwritten (47.4 x 39.5 cm), both in Greek. There are also two printed broadsides of statutes of the Society in Greek ("Diorganismos tēs en Athēnais Hetaireias tēs Physikēs Historias") and German ("Statuten der Naturhistorischen Gesellschaft zu Athen"), (42 x 31.5 cm each) written in three columns (circa 1836).
- Palmer-Sikelianou, Eua ASL to Inō Tsaoussē, 1946-1948; Palmer-Sikelianou, Eua (1874-1952); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Includes outgoing correspondence (ASL) to Inō Tsaoussē from Eva Palmer-Sikelianou, while the latter was living in New York.
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2020-25)
  Correspondence.; Dancers -- United States -- 20th century -- Correspondence.
- Marinatos, Spyros ALS, undated; Marinatos, Spyridōn (1901-1974); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2020-18)
  Spyros Marinatos autograph signed letter, to an unidentified colleague, with a mention to his trip in the United States. Letter is written on a letterhead of The Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, in May 15th (without year).
  Correspondence.
- Chapouthier, Fernand ALS to [Vourlakēs], [1929]-1948; Chapouthier, Fernand (1899-1953); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Consists of (17) autograph letters in Greek signed by Fernand Chapouthier, archaeologist and Hellenist, to his friend and colleague Giōrgos [Vourlakēs] in Crete. The letters were sent from several places, Bordeaux (9), Dijon (1), "Anaskaphē Malliōn=excavations in Mallia (1), Athens (5), Milan (1) (eight postcards (14.4 x 9.1 cm.) with an autograph letter on the reverse) and one without a title. Included also are: (1) autograph letter from the archaeologist Pierre Demargne to an unidentified priest dated 1948 and (1) photograph depicting Giōrgos Vourlakēs in Mallia dated 1931.
  Correspondence.; Chapouthier, Fernand (1899-1953)
- Iōannou, Giōrgos Autograph Manuscripts, 1973; Iōannou, Giōrgos (1927-1985); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Consists of two handwritten short stories, Epitaphios thrēnos (undated) and Hoi nerophides (1973) written in 12 loose leaves numbered 1-12 and 6 leaves numbered 1-6, respectively.
  Greek literature, Modern -- 20th century.; Manuscripts, Greek -- 20th-century.
- Laskaratos, Andreas Letters to Spyridōn De-Viazēs, 1883-1895; Laskaratos, Andreas (1811-1901); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2019-24)
  Consists of autograph letters from Andreas Laskaratos to S. De-Viazēs. There is also a poem by Laskaratos titled "Ho kalogēros" in his last letter dated September 7, 1895.
  Correspondence.; Authors, Greek (Modern) -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Authors, Greek (Modern) -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Laskaratos, Andreas (1811-1901); De-Viazēs, S. (Spyridōn) (1843-1927)
- Doxas Angelos collection, 1927-1948; Doxas, Angelos (1900-1985); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund. (AM 2019-25)
  Consists of (1) passport of Nikolaos Drakoulidēs (the real name of Doxas); (2) press passes for the journal "Acropolis" and the newspaper "Empros"; (1) certificate from the Greek-Southafrican League; (1) letter from the Greek-American Cultural Institute; (1) letter from the Philological Association "Parnassos"; and (1) certificate from the Society for the Protection of the Released.
  Documents -- 20th century.; Greek-American Cultural Institute; Philologikos Syllogos "Parnassos" (Athens, Greece)
- Katalogos tōn en tō Giatakiō tou Patriarcheiou tēs nēsou Chalkēs pragmatōn, 1874 April 10; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Gift of the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund.
  Consists of (5) loose leaves of a handwritten item inventory of the several rooms of the Patriarchate of the island Chalkē (Turkey) signed by the Archimandrite and Abbot of Saint George Makarios ("Parelavon ta anoterō / archimandritēs kai hēgoumenos tou / hagiou Geōrgiou Makarios").
- To paidomazōma, 1949; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Consists of a typescript (12 pages) describing the communist evacuation of the children during the Greek Civil War.
  Greece -- History -- Civil War, 1944-1949 -- Sources.; Children -- Greece; Communism -- Greece -- History -- 20th century
- Varvianēs, N. A., "Hē Zakynthos kai ho Vezal", 1965; Varvianēs, N. A.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Consists of a typescrtipt of a speech delivered by Nikolaos Varvianēs during commemorative celebrations for the 400th anniversary of Andreas Vesalius' death. The event took place in the island of Zakynthos on May 1, 1965. Included also are five black-and-white photographs of Zakynthos.
  Zakynthos Island (Greece) -- History; Vesalius, Andreas (1514-1564)
- Letters to Katerina [Angelakē-Rouk] from Melissanthē, Odysseas Elytēs, and Kōstas Tachtsēs, 1970; 1979; Elytēs, Odysseas, 1911-1996; Melissanthē (1907-1990); Tachtsēs, Kōstas 1927-1988; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Consists of three handwritten letters to Katerina (without last name) signed by the Greek poets Melissanthē, Elytēs, and Tachtsēs.
  Poets -- Greek (Modern) -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Correspondence -- 20th century; Angelakē-Rouk, Katerina (1939-2020)
- Pappadopoulos, G. G., 1865; 1873; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Consists of a program of Greek education for the second part of the school-year 1865-1866; and (2) handwritten letters to G. Papadopoulos, one signed by the President of the Greek Cabinet. There is also an issue of the newspaper "Ethnophylax" (etos B', arithmos 454, Pemptē 27 Phevrouariou, Athēnēsi 1864).
  Education -- Greece -- History -- 20th century.; Pappadopoulos, G. G. (Grēgorios G.) (1819-1873)
- Pallēs, Alexandros Documents, 1935 July 18; Pallēs, Alexandros (1851-1935); 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Consists of an original certified copy of Palles' last will (September 2, 1932) bearing the seal of John Arthur Davies, Notary Public in Liverpool in 1935; there are also (10) black-and-white family photographs including Palles' portraits and his grave in Iōannina, Greece. All photographs bear handwritten notes in black ink on the reverse.
  Wills.; photographs